Hello and welcome to the 27th tutorial
on how to program in Gcript 2. In the
last tutorial, I created an NPC that was
a button and when you clicked it, it
would say uh quest completed and then
that would go away. It would also be
pressed down. What I overlooked is that
when I press it, it doesn't get pressed
down, but after the text disappears, it
does. Well, the reason for this is in my
NPC script, I have it find the weapon
um
function from this weapon here. It's
running what's in these
brackets. Then it's coming back here and
running the rest of the script. It's not
going on it's not going through the
script
um as it's doing the weapon. It's sort
of pausing it. So, what I mean is it's
going here, pausing the script until
this entire uh function has run, then
it's going back to the script and
running the rest. Well, to fix this, I
could just copy the button down here,
place it on top, and as soon as I click
the MPC, it'll change the
image. Run the text.
Wait two
seconds, then push the button up again.
I'll show that in
action. As you can see, I press it, and
now it's getting pressed down, pressed
up, and it works. Well, that's not what
I wanted to
um explain in this tutorial. In this
tutorial, I want to start explaining
classes. Now, classes are the third type
of script in your script 2. From weapons
to
NPCs to classes, well, there are two
types of NPCs, level NPCs and NPCs on
the server, but that doesn't matter. In
the classes,
uh we have some scripts, too. Now, what
classes are are scripts that can be
accessed from any other NPC or any other
uh weapon. And I'll show you how that
works in a second. First, let's close
this old script and we'll create a new
weapon and call it rock
place. Okay. Now here let's
add client side function on key
pressed code,
key
and then let's put if key is equal to
F, then we're going to trigger
server on this weapon this name and
we're not going to send any variables
over. So what this is doing on key
pressed is as soon as I press a key on
the keyboard, it's going to run what's
in these brackets. Now what the code is
is it's the code of the key you're
pressing. So if I would put code is
equal
to 102 that would be the same as if I
pressed F. And what key is doing is it's
the
actual
ASKI image of the key. So if I put key
equals to F, it will do the same thing.
But because I don't want it to be too
confusing, I'll just put key equals F.
Okay. So it's going to run this trigger
server and go to server side. Here let's
put function on
action server
side. And let's end that for now. Let's
apply
this. Then let's go to classes and
create a new
class. Let's call it rock.
Okay. Now here let's add function on
created set image. Then let's put block
dot well I'm going to use rock image
that I have orbital
rock.png. Then let's just save this. Now
this is the entire script for now of
rock. This is a class keep in mind. and
it can be used in any other NPC or
weapon. Now, in this weapon to call that
class and run it, we're going to put put
NPC
to xcoordinate player.x y-coordinate
player.y. Then we're going to put some
crazy text right now. Um, let's just
close that.
We're going to put
join
slash rock
slash quote
uh all of this stuff.
Now, what this is going to do is it's
going to call this class and drop it as
an
NPC at these coordinates, which is
pretty good, pretty useful. You can make
bombs, you can make items that you can
drop on the ground that other players
can interact
with. So, let's just apply
this and let's add the weapon to
ourselves.
function on
created find player
myself and add
weapon rock place or just this
name. Uh this is finding us as a
prefix and then running the command add
weapon for this weapon name and adding
it to ourselves. This is going to add
the weapon to ourselves and so we don't
have to go to RC and you know mess
around with that. You can also use this
to add weapons to players as soon as
they enter the server or enter a level
or maybe buy an item from item shop. We
can also put remove weapon in case you
want to do that. Okay, so let's put add
weapon. Then we can just close this.
Apply again.
and let's try it out. So, when I press
F, it should drop a rock. And there's
the rock. You can see it can't be
deleted or anything, which is not a good
thing. You should always want to be able
to delete uh NPCs, I mean classes, cuz
they're going to stay there forever
unless you do don't. Now, the way to
delete unneeded
um classes that have been have been
dropped or glitched out is to go into RC
and put clear NPCs and whatever level
you're in. Testing NW and that should
delete it. Now, we should be more
careful next time. We don't want to put
add down classes that
um can't be deleted. So let's put
function
uh on was
hit. This is a function that will run as
soon as I slash the NPC with my sword.
And let's put
this.destroy. So this as in the current
uh
NPC and destroy as in destroying it.
This will remove the
NPC and which is pretty good. We need to
do that if we don't want the NPC to be
there forever. Keep in mind if this is
under client
side and we do it, it will actually not
be deleted. The player won't see it, but
on the server it will not have been
deleted. We do not want to have this
destroy on client side unless we just
want the player to for the moment see it
be deleted. Anyway, let's take that
out. Hit
apply. Minimize this and press F. We can
see an NPC has been dropped with the
script from the class we just made. We
can hit it and it'll disappear. We can
drop a ton more by pressing F and then
destroy them by hitting them. We can
make it do a lot more
things with this. We can have it maybe
say stuff.
this. Chad is equal
to
hello. Uh we like it's it's pretty much
like a normal
NPC and we can treat it as such. Anyway,
that concludes this tutorial and I hope
you understand how to
uh you have a bit of an understanding on
how to how to use classes and how to
call them
from other NPCs or
weapons. Keep in mind this is only
dropping the classes as NPCs. You can
use classes for a lot more things which
we'll get into later. Anyway, that
concludes this tutorial and I'll see you
later.